Joseph White
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Joseph White papers
circa 1870-2010, bulk 1971-2008
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
White, Joseph
1.7 linear feet
The papers of Washington, DC, based painter Joseph White measure 1.7 linear feet and date from circa 1870 to 2010, with the bulk of the material from 1971 to 2008. White's career as an artist is documented through scattered biographical material, correspondence with family and friends, poetry, plays, exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and photographs of White, family, friends, artwork, and source material.
Provenance
Donated by Joseph White in 2010.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Joseph White (1938- ) is a painter in Washington, DC. White works with a grid system and photographs to create his paintings. In 1963 he received a B.A. from the San Francisco State University. He then moved to New York City where he exhibited abstract paintings at the 1964 and 1967 Whitney Biennials. In 1976 he moved to Washington, D.C., and focused on representational painting. He has frequently exhibited his works in Washington, DC, San Francisco, CA, and New York, NY, and is included in the permanent collections of the Whitney Museum of American Art, National Gallery of Art, Corcoran Gallery of Art, and San Francisco Museum of Art, among others.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Washington, DC, based painter Joseph White measure 1.7 linear feet and date from circa 1870 to 2010, with the bulk of the material from 1971 to 2008. White's career as an artist is documented through scattered biographical material, correspondence with family and friends, poetry, plays, exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and photographs of White, family, friends, artwork, and source material.
Biographical material consists of documentation on White's band, Twisted Teenage Plot, as well as resumes documenting his career as a painter. Correspondence includes five letters sent to White from various people, a few postcards from White to his wife, Renee Butler, postcards to his brother, Lito White, and postcards to White from fellow artist and bandmate, Michael Clark. Writings include plays and poetry in manuscript and typescript form. Several of these writings are illustrated. Printed material consists of catalogs and announcements for exhibitions of artwork by White, as well as newspaper and magazine articles about his career. Photographs include family portraits from the late 1800s and photographs from White's childhood. Also found are handmade books of digital prints of his paintings and watercolors. Source photographs for White's paintings depict people, places, and objects. Many of these photographs include grid lines and masked-out details.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1973-2004 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1971-1999 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1970s-1990s (Boxes 1, 3; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1944-2006 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1870-2010 (Boxes 1-3; 0.8 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Butler, Renee; White, Lito
Subjects-Topical:
Painters--Washington (D.C.)
Types of Materials:
Manuscripts; Photographs; Resumes; Typescripts
Names:
Clark, Michael, 1946-
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1973-2004, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Found here are clippings, a press release, flyers, and a 45 rpm recording by Joseph White's band, Twisted Teenage Plot. Also found are White's resumes written at several points in his career.
  - Documentation on Twisted Teenage Plot, 1984-1987, (includes 1 sound disk: 45 rpm) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Resumes, circa 1973-2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, circa 1971-1999, Series 2:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  This series contains five letters sent to White from various people. One letter contains biographical information about a relative, Bishop William White. Also found are a few postcards sent by White to his wife, Renee Butler, postcards to his brother, Lito White, and postcards to White from fellow artist and bandmate, Michael Clark.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Letters, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Postcards to Renee Butler, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Postcards from Michael Clark, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Postcards to Lito and Leslie White, circa 1971-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Writings, circa 1970s-1990s, Series 3:; (Boxes 1, 3; 0.7 linear feet)
  Writings include typescripts and manuscripts of unpublished poems and plays by Joseph White. Many of the draft manuscripts were written in notebooks, and some of his writings are illustrated. Also found is a cloth bag which originally contained a few of White's notebooks.
  Titled works are arranged alphabetically.
  - Notebook, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Poetry, circa 1970s-1990s, (Oversized materials housed in Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Writing Fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Lise Defteri: The rhino tour Nepal," Draft Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Lise Defteri: The rhino tour Nepal," Typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Metro Blue," Draft Notebook, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Metro Blue," Typescripts, circa 1970s, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - "Metro Gold," undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Oriental Palace," circa 1973, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - "Play One Sandra: 1970 New York," 1980, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - "Sixty Leaves," Draft Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "Sixty Leaves," Typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "The Swim Club Songs," 1980, (Oversized materials housed in Box 3) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Cloth Bag for Notebooks, undated (Box 3)
  - Poetry, circa 1970s-1990s, (Oversized materials from box 1, folder 8) (Box 3)
  - "The Swim Club Songs," 1980, (Oversized materials from box 1, folder 22) (Box 3)
- Printed Material, 1944-2006, Series 4:; (Box 1; 6 folders)
  This series contains catalogs and announcements for exhibitions of artwork by Joseph White. Also found are newspaper and magazine articles about White, including a folder of reviews of his 2004 solo show at the Edison Place Gallery in Washington, DC.
  Items are arranged chronologically.
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, circa 1972-2006 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Magazines, 1968, 1977, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1944-1964, circa 1978-1991 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Reviews of 2004 Solo Exhibition, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Photographs, circa 1870-2010, Series 5:; (Boxes 1-3; 0.8 linear feet)
  Photographs are of White, his family, friends, works of art, and source material. Included are family portraits from the late 1800s and photographs from White's childhood. Also found are handmade books of digital prints of his paintings and watercolors. These digital images are also found on DVD. Source photographs for White's paintings depict people, places, and objects. Many of these photographs include grid lines and masked-out details. Miscellaneous photographs include a few images of musical instruments made by White.
  - Photographs of Joseph White, circa 1941-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Photographs of Family and Friends, circa 1870-1990s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Photograph Album of Digital Prints, "Joseph White Paintings: 1963-2003," circa 2008 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Photograph Album of Digital Prints, "Joseph White Paintings: 2004-2008," circa 2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photograph Album of Digital Prints, "Joseph White Watercolors: 1967-1985," circa 2008 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Photograph Album of Digital Prints, "Joseph White Watercolors: 2004-2008," circa 2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Paintings and Watercolors, 2010, (1 DVD) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Source Photographs for Paintings, circa 1974-2000s, (6 folders; oversized materials housed in Box 3) (Box 2, Folder 4-9)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Source Photographs for Paintings, circa 1974-2000s, (Oversized materials from box 2, folders 4-9) (Box 3)